hi welcome back to lumram and
let's put that picture up you guys
this is a peach tree uh so
you know we have this new little cafe uh
in arizona
which i bought because it was gonna
close and
all the old people in my town go there
for coffee in the morning
and talk to each other it's the only
bright spot in their day
so i i told the guy i would buy it and
oh god
it's a lot of work and
anyway we we called it peachtree cafe
and we
we planted these peach trees and they're
growing like crazy
and they flowered actually two chinese
friends
uh allison joe xiaoping and stanley chen
plant they they planted the trees
uh because they got stuck here during
the barns and
uh they had a lot of fun i guess they
never planted anything before
and it was a lot of fun to plant the
trees together
so you guys should know that your peach
trees are growing very crazy and it
looks like it's going to be about
20 peaches on the in the first year
which is very strange uh anyway
why are we talking about that let's go
back to the text
separate
this is talking about different kinds of
karma so most of the karmas
that you and i make
we do something nice for somebody we
collect the seed in our mind
and then later on that seed opens we get
the result
it's it should be much bigger than the
cause right
and then it's done and it's over with
okay and then you're gonna have to go
find
someone else to to do something nice to
them
because that other seat is finished now
okay
and that's the way seeds work you know
they
grow a tree and when the tree grows
it kills the seed and and that's the
same with seeds in our mind
we get the result of the good karma
and then that's finished and now we have
to go make another good karma but
bodhichitta is different bodhichitta is
a self-replicating karma
okay bodhichitta is a karma that when it
opens it causes more buddha
so it tends to perpetuate itself it's
like a
positive wheel of life okay but
other plants bloom and die
and he calls means like a bamboo
or sugar cane and then a peach tree for
example
it will give a fruit i remember my
teacher
he was teaching this subject it was very
beautiful and he had a
he had a peach tree outside and he took
a peach
and he ate it and he took the pit and he
went over and he planted it
and that grew into a big beautiful tree
so he said look you see the fruit
becomes the seed
so that's the way bodhichitta is the
fruit becomes the seed
and then it's an upward cycle it keeps
growing more trees
and keeps growing more fruit okay chia
juice
he compares uh bodhichitta to a fruit
tree
taparian it keeps getting results
those results become next year's seeds
may say power gear it never stops it
keeps
upwards spiral okay all right
and that's from master shanti demo again
okay
uh shay simba shin sinham console zopala
at the end of the class we always say
[Music]
may i collect the two collections of
merit
and wisdom and
somebody asked me a question when you
get to the level of an enlightened being
are you still making karma do you still
call it karma and
and we don't call it karma because karma
always has
some negative connotations
even good karma sometimes we call it
dirty good karma
because it wears out okay so
at when you get up to the karmas or the
seeds
that turn you into buddha we don't call
them karma anymore
we call them the two collections okay so
here he's mentioning and by the way
where is that famous verse tim for a
hundred dollars
about the two collections
come on you guys at the what
nope but you're close
it is the gardener it is ariana gardena
uh yeah at the end of the 60 verses uh
which
uh nick uh lashaw is translating
nowadays he's translating an impossible
commentary like delta
he told me yesterday he was wrestling
with delta jake i said don't try he's
stronger
uh anyway uh
cinema console zopala so if you want to
complete
the collection of merit which creates
the body or the mind of a buddha
the body of a buddha okay
there's nothing better in the world than
bodhichitta
okay
if you don't have bodhi tuna
and somehow you could make an offering
to a hundred thousand people
okay uh kappa boom chat mambo
and even if you could do that for many
millions of years
and even if
even if you took a bag and filled it up
with all the jewels
that exist on a thousand
planets sorry a thousand groups of a
thousand planets it's called the dongsum
uh a billion planets if you could take a
billion planets worth
of gemstones and offer it to a hundred
thousand people
for billions of years okay jimba
jimbayan
jay busey at some point that karma would
run out
okay the karma would run out and then
you'd have to
do it over again but you know what he's
going to say
girls say if you are guilty
even if you are not able to do the six
perfections for example
uh and even if it's not the kind of
karma
that would create a buddha right away
some descended
even if you have one of those let's call
it a blessed moment
where you feel close to being a
bodhisattva
okay like you're in the
sacred mood you're having a sacred
moment in your life
i don't know about you but it doesn't
happen very often for me it happens
maybe once in a few months or something
so you're having one of these sacred
moments
a moment of real peace and and silence
or something
and then uh he says
you're having one of those mom when
you're in the super good spiritual mood
and you're eating french fries like
mcdonald's which is the only thing you
can eat at mcdonald's
uh and you dunder la senchi
you got the picture for me you guys this
is one of my favorite things to do
okay uh this is giving a mcdonald's
french fry
to a bird okay and
this is the kind of thing that lord
buddha used to do he would
go to mcdonald's buy french fries
eat most of them and then throw a couple
to the birds who are always hanging out
at mcdonald's
and then uh you make a little prayer
okay i'm teaching you a really fun
spiritual practice okay so go to
mcdonald's
you know eat a few and throw out the
rest but take a few french fries
and just before you throw it to the bird
you make a prayer
and you say if you eat this french fry
you have to be one of my first disciples
after i become a buddha and then throw
the french fries to them
and then it's so fun to see them eat the
french fries sometimes you have a really
bad day and they refuse to eat the
french fry
but mostly they will eat it okay so
hold up the french fry make a little
prayer
a say a little prayer and then
throw the french foot and then uh he
says here
if you if you throw the french fry
to the little bird outside of mcdonald's
with a prayer uh bodhisattva's prayer
it's more powerful than giving all the
gemstones
on a billion planets for a billion years
to a billion people okay got it it's
more powerful
all right you know sen sen means
sen means a tiny piece of food
why because that karma is
self-replicating
that karma tends to create more karma of
the same
okay it doesn't wear out it's not like
they call sugarcane which is harvested
once and then the plant dies
the gas if you know about that
old sugarcane anyway it's popular
in
hawaii big waves in hawaii
that's where i met it anyway uh jebus
said to me
this this this seed has no end this is
like a peach tree
and the fruit becomes the seed from the
next dream okay
then you'll be able to practice the six
perfections
and it will turn you into buddha
it's very difficult to express
this next point it's difficult to uh
it's difficult to say it to somebody who
hasn't experienced it okay
but you try to imagine that if you did
something
that affected a billion if you did
that affected billions of people what
would that karma be like
and then he says look if you take
one stick of incense and you offer it to
one person
is it good or not it's a good deed
you know will it uh will the second love
karma kick in
what's the second law of code will it
increase exponentially yeah it will
okay that's with one stick of incense
now try to imagine that somehow
when you offered one stick of incense to
somebody
at the same moment you could offer it to
everyone in the universe
would that be a good deed that's a nice
thing
you know look offer one stick of incense
to one per
normal person then the law second law of
karma kicks in
it will multiply exponentially
and you'll get 16 and then you'll get
153 and you know
like that now imagine that
when you offer the one stick to one
person
somehow your body multiplies
and you're offering it to everyone in
the universe countless people
no no limit imagine that okay
then he said you get the good karma
that you know have to multiply the karma
of
giving the one stick to the one person
which multiplies by itself already
and then multiply that times how many
infinite multiply one by infinite and
that's how much karma you get
by offering one stick of incense if you
have bunny teeth
and and i it's hard for me it's kind of
frustrating for me because
i have to keep repeating something and
uh
i'm not sure i'm not sure it really
sinks in
but if you think of the nicest people
you ever met
or the kindest things you've ever heard
about
on this planet okay like people like
buddha or jesus or muhammad
helping millions of people right
for hundreds of generations right uh
imagine that kind of goodness and then
imagine someone who's doing that
for countless people on countless
planets
okay and then try to imagine the
difference
in the number okay what is the one
compared to
what is a million compared to infinity
so i'm trying to get you to think about
infinity and i don't know how to get a
normal person
to think about infinity sometimes i
think
you can say take off in a spaceship
away from earth and let me know when you
see the last star
okay like sometimes that's the only way
i personally can think about infinity
i think about getting in a spaceship and
just going that way
and then there's no last star they just
keep going so try to imagine
a karma like that try to imagine a
mental scene
which is infinite as many as the stars
and there is no limit to the stars
there's no end to the stars
there's the end to the stars that blew
up in our particular
universe but there are many universes
and there are endless stars okay
try to imagine uh a person
try to imagine yourself taking one
action
which affects infinite deeds
okay and that's how much good karma you
make
and there's and you can't compare it to
anyone
doing anything on this planet there's no
comparison
okay all right um so if
if if normal people
can study lomrim and get body china
then what you're doing to help people
cannot be mentioned cannot be compared
to anybody else in this world
okay there's no comparison you can't
compare
just to have that experience for 20
minutes
of of making a connection with every
living
being if those beings are infinite
then how could you do anything better
than that okay that's the point
all right dana
and uh he says if you do tsar cheek
means
one uh string one
rosary of money okay uh
sarchik tung kyung or it could mean a
single money
uh sam jenkins pinyon tom
the karma of bodhisattva collects by
saying
mantras for each mantra they say
is multiplied by the number of beings
in the universe which is infinite
got it so boy you can finish your 300
000 mattress
in much less than three years right cat
okay
uh all right
then uh i was trying to find a picture
for infinity
i i i kind of gave up but here's a
picture i don't know
all right that's infinity
i tried i tried the infinity sign but it
looks like a
car thing or something like that anyway
what is one times infinity
yeah i mean there's no number
everyone in this course
listening right now we would all like to
be a good person
and we would all like to do something
good for other people we are we have
selfish
moments uh many times during the day
where we're just thinking about
ourselves but most of the people
listening right now i think all of us
would like to be a nice person
and we would like to do something to
help the world
so we do all these projects we fundraise
we
help poor people we help sick people we
save ancient books
but a minute of buddy china
is one times 10
to the infinity power more good garment
than that
so just the attitude of wanting to help
all the beings in the universe
it's more powerful than everything else
we did in our life
okay and that's why this alarm room is
important okay
is it possible for a normal human being
to encounter an infinite number of other
people
and the answer is yes why because of
emptiness
okay it's possible you can do it and
it's not a big deal
it's just discipline and hard work
okay but you can do it okay you you can
spend your life struggling to fundraise
a certain amount
okay or to do a certain number of
mantras that's a good thing it's a it's
a powerful thing and i do do it
but uh if you could reach this state of
mind
uh the comparison is there is no
comparison
because it's infinite okay so which one
should i do
both okay shut up
fundraise and infinite at the same time
all right
monsante
in the days when lord buddha his holy
presence was still here
ubochiki a poor person and i found the
story
and it was hard to find and i found it
and in fact it was a it was a
it was a beautiful it was a poor woman
they don't say it but it was a lady
cheeky semde simbegone with the
intention
of a bodhisattva kombucha she offered
one tiny little
buttercup butter lamp cup
butter lamb in a small cup to the buddha
chungo kampua and uh
she she made it i'll read it to you okay
well i'll just tell you she made a
prayer
made this lamp not go out until i come
back as a buddha
you know may this butter lamp not run
out
until i return as a buddha she made this
prayer and then she lit the lamp and she
went off to
go study or she probably went to diamond
mountain to do a retreat
by the way i'm looking forward to maybe
in the fall we can have a
in-person retreat especially if people
have been vaccinated etc
and i i think diamond mountain is is
hungry for you guys
diamond mountain is so beautiful right
now and so
comfortable like i don't know when i got
here i felt
i just spent a week at a very expensive
hotel in
in san diego because i was helping my
mom
and uh and i that mountain is on the
same level it's kind of amazing
you know it's really beautiful now so
anyway
imagine she goes off the diamond
mountain she leaves the buttercup at
home
and she says made burn until i return as
a buddha or something
may i become a buddha and then
you know
okay comes back in the room and buddha
says hey you know
that butter lamp is still going could
you blow it out
you know it could start a fire you know
so here's the real story i'll read it to
you
this comes from
called a sutra called supported by the
town that's a long story
how long is this is this going to mess
up our schedule
yes i don't care let's do it
until the future moment when i return as
a buddha
doc until i come back
pardon car borrow our girl may this
butter lamp
continue to burn it's a tiny little cup
she lit the lamp and tongue get the song
she went off on her
retreat sorry i'm talking too fast
uh my me is their key
by the way i've left them don't look for
it in the alarm room i went to the sutra
okay uh the light from the butternut
zombo
covered the whole planet
okay
[Music]
and the next morning it was still going
it's probably keeping everybody
up
[Music]
buddha said to mount ganyana
you know can you blow it out it's you
know it's
dangerous and also nobody can get any
sleep
uh poor chamber cookie top he took the
edge of his
monk shawl and he tried to
blow out the butternut mermaid
[Music]
who was a master of miracles called up a
cyclone
a tornado and he said blow out the lamp
guess what happened
he went up to the
form form realm to brahma level
way above this planet doing they don't
seem
deer he got in a place where he could
see all
the billion planets
okay including our planet on which the
butternut was
still burning but he he called down
a cosmic rain on the
universe on the galaxy of a billion
stars
he called down a ring each dropped
shinte each drop was as big
as a
wagon what do you call the the piece of
wood that goes out
the tongue that holds those six horses
or something
the stick that goes between the horses
yeah anyway a big piece of a cart call
it a a bmw
each drop was as big as as
it all fell on that one butter lamp say
couldn't put it out then they
give it up that's the same verb that uh
atisha used before my
this particular butter lamp
was lit by a person with body today
okay changing your sending intake is
looking
[Music]
because nothing else in the world
can compare to the power of bodhichitta
okay cool story
okay all right i'm not going to tell you
the rest because it's
too well let's do it it's so cool
[Music]
then the lady came back okay
uh to see what was happening with her
but in there
and they
and she was extremely overwhelmed by
joy
and then did the buddha smile
okay i love it you know they don't say
he
said anything he said
they're like what did buddha do what did
him do
he smiled what
he just smiled
and what's a buddhist smile look like
so it's part of the sutra i love it
what was the buddhist response he just
smiled
what was the smile like what's it look
like when i bring a smile
you want to know what a buddhist smile
looks like
who is there of light flies out from
their
well-brushed teeth okay
what's it look like
you get blue lights simple
you get yellow lights
marple you get red lights
garbo you get white lights
tsuka means the green of a
fresh of a spring tree like around here
the
mesquite right uh shell
crystal mu the sheen
on silver that's what happens when a
buddhist smile
okay and that's the end of the story yay
all right then he says chin jingle can
by the way the same point is made
in
suppose you are able to give birth to
the state of mind
in which you want to help infinite
beings
next picture
this guy oh no yeah i don't know it's
almost as handsome as pudgy
uh or jordan i guess
what's he doing hundred dollars what's
he doing
he's dead out asleep he's not meditating
he copy meditation
he's not thinking about the uh
irritating people in the project
negation michael gaining
he's dead out asleep and he's
piling up huge amounts of good karma
because he has bodhichitta so the next
part of
the the lamrim is talking about
if you have bodhichitta then it really
doesn't matter what you're doing
all day long i mean as long as you're
not burning down somebody's house
but uh even if you're sleeping
you are collecting huge amounts of good
comment
here's how shantideva said
once you get to bodhichitta you can be
sitting
sleeping i like this i like this
promise because i enjoy sleeping
so if i can collect good karma while i
sleep i'm interested
knee loka pod make your cam pop make
kirk um
even if you're just totally distracted
by a netflix movie or something
okay this is the perfect dharma solution
you can sleep all day when you're awake
you can watch
netflix
you still get the power of collecting
good karma
you me without a
without a moment's interruption to
tumashi nam kanyama
a quantity of good karma
equal to the extent of
of the universe
even while you're sleeping and even
while you're wasting time on some silly
netflix movie okay
then uh you're still making huge amounts
of good coverage i like it
i'm interested teach me how
yeah okay here you go and uh that's
another quotation from master shantae
and and he says here's an important part
for you medicine
buddha people he shanti deva promises
that you are collecting that kind of
karma
even if all you did was
make a commitment to the idea of
bodhichitta
okay the first of the two sets of vowels
right the first vowel
i commit to the i commit in principle
to to the bodhisattvas way of life in
principle
i'm not willing to do anything yet but
in principle i commit
that's called the dukedom right the
committing to the aspirations
and we took it in last december we all
took it he says
even a person who just took
that much but each other
they just took the vow to think about
being about something
they're already into the sleep and
netflix category
even if you're just asleep or if you're
wasting your time
watching the movie or something by the
way there is a time when you should
watch a movie
so you can rest and that's okay watch a
nice movie
okay don't don't watch a movie that's
going to put bad seeds in your mind
jerk the karma will never
be interrupted okay so now
now he comes to a famous idea from
master shantideva
semjen chicky lennon
i think we have a picture you ready
this is a mom uh her daughter had a
headache
mom gave the daughter one aspirin okay
children's aspirin and she's gonna give
her some water to
take it looks like emma right not quite
yet
she's not that big yet but ava's eyes
are more powerful uh
anyway some gen cheeky lane some sound
even if your intention is no
more than giving a single aspirin
to a single person to remove their
headache
penian chimbo you get extremely powerful
karma from that one act
but if you rather have this intention
to take away the headaches of infinite
beings
wouldn't you say that's a lot okay a lot
of good karma
and then he quotes uh shanti dev again
master chanting
even if you just think i would
like to take away the headaches of a
person penduk samba dandente
if you get a lot of good karma
just from the intention to take away a
headache
from a single person generated
if you wish to remove the unhappiness
of infinite living beings
well how much karma is that much good
means
you know what you want me to tell you
how can i tell you
i can't tell you okay got it
all right um we still have five minutes
i can use it right tim all right
you guys should thank tim someday we're
gonna start hey
the next class we'll just start the next
class class five
i call class five
uh but which makes us officially one
class behind i'm thinking
uh a ketchup stain in the middle of the
sun
you spill ketchup on your shirt you have
a stain
if you want to remove it put your shirt
in the middle of the sun and maybe
you'll get rid of the ketchup stain okay
and i looked it up
at how many degrees it's like 50 billion
billion i don't know
the shirt would vaporize long before
right
sustain would obviously pay price so
we're going to continue on this theme
of how powerful is bodhichitta
in removing negative karma okay
uh may say
then uh they quote uh what's the
quotation
from i think
and he says look
if you um prepared
i don't know about you i'm a slow cook
it takes me a long time to cook
when i offered to cook which is not a
very smart thing for me to do
it takes me three four hours to make a
good meal and clean up
the frustrating thing is the eating
takes 15 minutes right
and but if i make a nice french meal for
veronica or something it takes three
four hours
and anyway if you made a meal
for some people and uh
you know you made it
grumply grumpy
grump grump grumply
if you were grumpy making the meal
it was enough to fill up their bellies
for half a day a couple hours
if you were grumpy and took a couple
hours to cook something nice
and filled up somebody else's tummy for
an hour or two
people would say oh what a nice person
right wouldn't they we do it all the
time
if someone i've never had anybody cook
for me it's kind of a miracle
and then i'm like well thank you i'm
really appreciative
now suppose you
made a meal for infinite number of
beings
that never stopped
[Music]
and that meal didn't fill up their belly
for a few hours
it brought them all their hopes and
dreams forever
okay then compared to cooking the meal
for somebody
how does it rate okay how does it mean
what the the point is shantideva is
saying
when somebody cooks somebody else a meal
a dinner
to honor them right which is a nice i
enjoy
cooking for people so to honor them you
cook for them
and then it puts everybody in a good
mood and they're like oh thank you so
much
i made a nice meal for my mom
she came to my house and my brother and
i i made them a nice meal
and it made everybody feel happy
well then multiply that times infinity
that's all
that's what body chill is all about okay
um i like to show
this picture and we'll stop there
uh a farm
this guy's not the guy there you go
uh the point is again
that when you plant this meal
from the soil okay the
the soil never stops
and and it's the biochar thing again
punchy okay
it's that the soil never stops working
the soil
works for everybody the soil doesn't say
ah you know you you planted me last year
i
i don't feel like doing it again you
know
the minerals and the chemicals of the
soil
will keep working for you forever
as long as you don't abuse it right
in india i've seen ancient fields that
are
dead they can't grow things anymore
they use them up but uh
but uh normally a normal field if you
take good care of it
it will just keep feeding you year after
year
and that's the idea with body chili okay
it's like a field
that never stops giving crops
it's got good biochar on it
if you don't know what biochar is you
should find out it's a wonderful
way to make your flowers
i swear in in the few weeks they're
twice as big
and twice as beautiful so thank you
touching you guys for
inventing that stuff all right